## Bastián González-Bustamante

#### Post-Doctoral Researcher in Computational Social Science · Leiden University

Wijnhaven, Turfmarkt 99, The Hague 2511 DP, Netherlands

## Summary.

I am a post-doctoral researcher in Computational Social Science at the Institute of Security and Global Affairs (ISGA) at the Faculty of Governance and Global Affairs at Leiden University, Netherlands. I hold a DPhil (PhD) in Politics from the University of Oxford, United Kingdom. Before my DPhil, I earned an MA (1st) in Political Science and a BA (2:1) in Government, both from the Universidad de Chile.

My research interests lie in the intersection of comparative politics and government, focusing mainly on cabinets, political regimes and civil services. Methodologically, my interests rely on the application of quantitative text analysis, machine learning methods and causal inference strategies in the comparative politics field. In the last few years, my work has been published in The International Journal of Press/Politics, World Development, Government and Opposition, The British Journal of Politics and International Relations, Bulletin of Latin American Research and elsewhere.

During my post-doctorate, I will be working on two research projects funded by the Dutch Research Council (NWO) related to how the rule of law has changed over time and automated text analysis of investment data to study the effects of governance on sustainable investments. Specifically, I will employ Natural Language Processing (NLP) and text-as-data techniques to find patterns and topics within big text data.

#### Education

**University of Oxford** Oxford, GBR **DPhil (PhD) in Politics** 2019 - 2023

Professor Petra Schleiter (Supervisor)

Universidad de Chile Santiago, CHL **MA in Political Science** 2010 - 2013

Highest Distinction (1st, First-class honours)

**Universidad de Chile** Santiago, CHL

**BA in Government** 2004 - 2009

Distinction (2:1, Second-class honours, upper division)

Universidad de Chile Santiago, CHL **BPS in Public Administration** 2004 - 2009

Distinction (2:1, Second-class honours, upper division)

## Featured Publications

- Orchard, X., & González-Bustamante, B. (2024). Power Hierarchies and Visibility in the News: Exploring Determinants of Politicians' Presence and Prominence in the Chilean Press (1991-2019). The International Journal of Press/Politics, 29(1), 100-123. DOI: 10.1177/19401612221089482.
- González-Bustamante, B. (2023). Ministerial stability during presidential approval crises: The moderating effect of ministers' attributes on dismissals in Brazil and Chile. The British Journal of Politics and International Relations, 25(4), 655-675. DOI: 10.1177/13691481221124850.
- González-Bustamante, B., & Aguilar, D. (2023). Territorial patterns of open e-government: evidence from Chilean municipalities. Political Research Exchange, 5(1). DOI: 10.1080/2474736X.2023.2194369. SOCARXIV: 10.31235/osf.io/gt8a5.
- Fleming, T. G., González-Bustamante, B., & Schleiter, P. (2022). Cabinet Reshuffles and Parliamentary No-Confidence Motions. Government and Opposition. FirstView. DOI: 10.1017/gov.2022.23.

- González-Bustamante, B. (2021). Evolution and early government responses to COVID-19 in South America. *World Development*, 137, 105180. poi: 10.1016/j.worlddev.2020.105180.
- González-Bustamante, B. (2020). The Politics-Administration Dichotomy: A Case Study of the Chilean Executive During the Democratic Post-Transition. *Bulletin of Latin American Research*, *39*(5), 582–597. DOI: 10.1111/blar.13044. SocARXIV: 10.31235/osf.io/d52au.
- Maillet, A., González-Bustamante, B., & Olivares, A. (2019). Public-Private Circulation and the Revolving Door in the Chilean Executive Branch (2000-2014). Latin American Business Review, 20(4), 367–387.
  DOI: 10.1080/10978526.2019.1652099.
- González-Bustamante, B. (2018). Civil Service Models in Latin America. In A. Farazmand (ed.), *Global Encyclopedia of Public Administration, Public Policy, and Governance*. Cham: Springer. DOI: 10.1007/978-3-319-20928-9\_2699. SocARXIV: 10.31235/osf.io/mp4qd.

# Relevant Teaching Experience

- School of Business, Universidad Mayor, Santiago, CHL
  - Machine Learning in Public Policy and Economics (workshop, Prof. Carla Cisternas), spring 2021
- Department of Politics and International Relations, University of Oxford, Oxford, GBR
  - o Comparative Government (undergraduate tutorial, Prof. Petra Schleiter), Hilary 2020
- Faculty of Adminstration and Economics, Universidad de Santiago de Chile, Santiago, CHL
  - o Political Science I (undergraduate lecture), spring 2014, 2018, fall 2015-2019
  - o Political Science II (undergraduate lecture), spring 2015-2018
  - Econometrics for Public Policies (undergraduate lecture), fall 2018
  - Workshop for Research Design (graduate seminar), spring 2017-2018
  - o Research Methodology (undergraduate lecture), spring 2014-2015, fall 2015-2017
  - o Introduction to Quantitative Methods (undergraduate lecture), fall 2017
- School of Government and Public Management, Universidad de Chile, Santiago, CHL
  - o Study of Political Phenomena (undergraduate lecture), fall 2016
  - o Political Analysis (undergraduate lecture), fall 2014
  - Elite Theory and Democracy (undergraduate lecture, Prof. Alejandro Olivares), spring 2013-2014

### Recent Honours & Awards \_\_\_\_\_

2023	<b>ECPR Joint Sessions of Workshops Grant.</b> Travel support for the European Consortium for Political Research (ECPR) Joint Sessions of Workshops, £ 1 350.	Toulouse, FRA
2022	SLAS Postgraduate and Postdoctoral Research Award and Conference Grant. Research support grant for my DPhil (PhD) project and travel support for the Society for Latin American Studies (SLAS) Annual Conference, £ 1 400.	Bath, GBR
2022	<b>St Hilda's College Muriel Wise Fund and Travel and Book Grants</b> . Research support grant for my DPhil (PhD) project and allowances for participation in conferences and purchase of books, £ 2 255.	Oxford, GBR
2019	<b>Becas Chile Doctoral Scholarship Abroad</b> . Tuition fees, transport and living expenses for pursuing a DPhil (PhD) at the University of Oxford (ANID/PFCHA/72200340), £ 160 000.	Oxford, GBR

# **Selected Conference Presentations**

#### \* Selection of only the last five years

2023	BigSurv — Conference	Quito, ECU
2023	European Consortium for Political Research (ECPR) — General Conference	Prague, CZE
2023	${\it International Political Science Association (IPSA) - World Congress}$	Buenos Aires, ARG
2023	European Consortium for Political Research (ECPR) — Joint Sessions	Toulouse, FRA
2023	Political Studies Association (PSA) — Annual International Conference	Liverpool, GBR
2023	Society for Latin American Studies (SLAS) — Annual Conference	Belfast, GBR
2022	Latin American Political Science Association (ALACIP) — Congress	Virtual
2022	The R User Conference 2022 (userR) — Annual Conference	Virtual
2022	Latin American Studies Association (LASA) — International Congress	Virtual
2022	Society for Latin American Studies (SLAS) — Annual Conference	Bath, GBR
2021	${\it International Political Science Association (IPSA) - World Congress}$	Virtual
2019	Latin American Studies Association (LASA) — International Congress	Boston, USA

## Languages & Software \_\_\_\_\_

**Languages** Spanish (native speaker), English (fluent), Portuguese (advanced reading skills), Italian (elemental reading skills), French (elemental reading skills)

**Programming &** R, Python, Stata, SPSS/PSPP, Gephi, UCINET, NetDraw, Tosmana, Fuzzy-Sets, ArcGIS, ATLAS.ti, **Software** EndNote, Zotero, HPOP, ŁTĘX, BibTĘX, JabRef, MS Office, WordPress, Moodle, HTML, CSS, XHTML